<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on The Salix Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on The Salix Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 14:49:37 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.salixos.org/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Just a Little Teaser</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/just-a-little-teaser/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 14:49:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/just-a-little-teaser/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned problems with the installer in my previous blog post. Well, they&amp;rsquo;re solved now. Here&amp;rsquo;s a little something to get you mildly excited. It&amp;rsquo;s the LightDM login screen:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are We There Yet?</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/are-we-there-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 14:36:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/are-we-there-yet/</guid>
      <description>Short answer: No.
Somewhat longer answer: Not yet, but we&amp;rsquo;re getting there. There&amp;rsquo;s still lot&amp;rsquo;s of things to do, but there will be an alpha release soon (hopefully).
Really long answer:
It has been almost two weeks now that Slackare 15.0 has been released (yay!) and there are now regular inquiries on IRC and in the forums concerning the release of Salix 15.0.
So, no, Salix 15.0 is not ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for 15.0</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/preparing-for-15.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/preparing-for-15.0/</guid>
      <description>It seems like, finally, the pieces are being put in place for the next Slackware release. It has been a long wait, it will be 5 years since the 14.2 release in a few months. Since Salix releases are tied to Slackware releases, there hasn&amp;rsquo;t been a Salix release for a long while too. Major changes that the next Slackware release will introduce include a switch to PAM, Linux kernel 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Display Managers</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/on-display-managers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/on-display-managers/</guid>
      <description>A Display Manager is the application that provides a graphic user interface (GUI) that is displayed at the end of the boot process and lets the user authenticate themselves by providing their username and password, before entering their preferred X11 session, for example Xfce, KDE, fluxbox, etc.
Up until Salix 14.2, we&amp;rsquo;ve been using a very old version of GDM as the default display manager. Actually we&amp;rsquo;ve been using the same major version of GDM, which is 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spam in the Forums</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/spam-in-the-forums/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/spam-in-the-forums/</guid>
      <description>Unfortunately, we&amp;rsquo;re having a huge problem with spammers in our forums. Most of the users that register are actually spammers. This has been going on for a while too.
About a year ago (or maybe more than that? I&amp;rsquo;m not sure), we moved to using Google&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;I am not a robot&amp;rdquo; checkbox reCAPTCHA. This is supposed to be the best countermeasure against bots. Before doing that, spammers were also a big problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New blog site</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 22:50:02 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to do this for a long time. The old blog site at blogspot was always supposed to be something temporary. It lasted five years&amp;hellip;
I never really liked the look of the old blog site that much. And there weren&amp;rsquo;t that many options to customize it in the first place. The WYSIWYG editor was ugly and difficult to work with. And it was hard to prepare content and post it later.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our new extra repository</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/our-new-extra-repository/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/our-new-extra-repository/</guid>
      <description>You might have noticed that just before the Salix Xfce 14.2RC1 release a new repository, named extra-14.2 has appeared in our servers. This has been enabled by default in the 14.2RC1 and 14.2RC2 releases and will be also available in the final 14.2 release.
This new repository is present for both i486 and x86_64 architectures and its purpose it to include packages built from SlackBuilds found at slackbuilds.org. At this moment, it&amp;rsquo;s not that full, only about 20 packages are included in it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our SBo mirrors</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/our-sbo-mirrors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/our-sbo-mirrors/</guid>
      <description>We have been mirroring the slackbuilds.org (SBo) repository and at the same time applying slight changes to it for some time now. These changes are essential to Salix, for a few reasons.
First of all, the SBo maintainers have decided that they will only list SlackBuild dependencies only if these are not part of a Slackware full installation. While this may be a decision that is fine for Slackware itself, since they don&amp;rsquo;t offer any kind of support for users doing anything other than a full Slackware installation, it&amp;rsquo;s generally not good for Salix, since a Salix installation of any edition, is slimmer than a full Slackware installation, by far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MATE is around the corner</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/mate-is-around-the-corner/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/mate-is-around-the-corner/</guid>
      <description>MATE 1.8 has been released in source code form by its developers about 3 weeks ago and I have been working on packages for Salix for about as long. The good news is that I think I&amp;rsquo;m almost done! So, expect MATE 1.8 packages to hit the repos sometime in the following days. We didn&amp;rsquo;t have any MATE release for Salix 14.0, but it looks like we are going to have one for 14.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Startup Guide</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-startup-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-startup-guide/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this for a while and were hoping to have it ready by the time 14.1 is released and it seems that we managed to make it! You can now find the new guide linked from our main website.
The startup guide was left with no updates since the 13.37 release, so it was getting a bit old. It was still mostly OK, but there were things that were out of date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kernel decisions</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/kernel-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/kernel-decisions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had a few chats lately, either through email, in our forums and in IRC about the kernels that we&amp;rsquo;re including with our 32-bit releases and I thought it would be best if I explained things a bit.
First of all, 32-bit Slackware ships with two different kernels. The first one, which is the most used of the two is an i686 optimized, PAE enabled, SMP capable kernel. The second one is an i486 optimized, non-PAE, non-SMP capable kernel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The gksu problem</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/the-gksu-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/the-gksu-problem/</guid>
      <description>We had a real problem with ktsuss/gksu while developing for 14.1. It seems that newer versions of the shadow package, and certainly the one that is included in Slackware 14.1, don&amp;rsquo;t allow su to be executed in any other way except directly from a terminal. That means that su cannot be executed as a subprocess from inside ktsuss or the original gksu anymore and these become effectively useless. This is a critical issue for us, because if we don&amp;rsquo;t fix it, almost nothing in the System part of the menu would actually work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much of Slackware is in Salix</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/how-much-of-slackware-is-in-salix/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/how-much-of-slackware-is-in-salix/</guid>
      <description>That is a question that I had in my mind for a while. At some point I had also done the actual counting, so I had an idea, but I never wrote anything down.
There are many people that believe that a derivative distribution only just leeches their parent distribution, maybe changing the default wallpaper or a couple of settings here and there and making a release. I know for a fact that some people that have never tried Salix (or have tried Salix but never Slackware itself) even think the same for Salix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Website Design</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-website-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/new-website-design/</guid>
      <description>As many might have noticed, we now have a new main website design!
Since the Salix project was started, the main website was actually a part of our wiki, which is using the MediaWiki engine. That had one main advantage, which at that time seemed enough to justify that choice; we would use a single CMS to manage both our wiki and our main page. So, we created a custom MediaWiki theme that would look good as a main project page and as a wiki.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
