<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>slackware on The Salix Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.salixos.org/tags/slackware/</link>
    <description>Recent content in slackware on The Salix Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 14:36:25 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.salixos.org/tags/slackware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Are We There Yet?</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/are-we-there-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 14:36:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/are-we-there-yet/</guid>
      <description>Short answer: No.
Somewhat longer answer: Not yet, but we&amp;rsquo;re getting there. There&amp;rsquo;s still lot&amp;rsquo;s of things to do, but there will be an alpha release soon (hopefully).
Really long answer:
It has been almost two weeks now that Slackare 15.0 has been released (yay!) and there are now regular inquiries on IRC and in the forums concerning the release of Salix 15.0.
So, no, Salix 15.0 is not ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for 15.0</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/preparing-for-15.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/preparing-for-15.0/</guid>
      <description>It seems like, finally, the pieces are being put in place for the next Slackware release. It has been a long wait, it will be 5 years since the 14.2 release in a few months. Since Salix releases are tied to Slackware releases, there hasn&amp;rsquo;t been a Salix release for a long while too. Major changes that the next Slackware release will introduce include a switch to PAM, Linux kernel 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much of Slackware is in Salix</title>
      <link>https://blog.salixos.org/post/how-much-of-slackware-is-in-salix/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.salixos.org/post/how-much-of-slackware-is-in-salix/</guid>
      <description>That is a question that I had in my mind for a while. At some point I had also done the actual counting, so I had an idea, but I never wrote anything down.
There are many people that believe that a derivative distribution only just leeches their parent distribution, maybe changing the default wallpaper or a couple of settings here and there and making a release. I know for a fact that some people that have never tried Salix (or have tried Salix but never Slackware itself) even think the same for Salix.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
